William Tully Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Tully Papers
1806-1859
GEN MSS 1403
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.08
Tully, William, 1785-1859
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sarah and Elizabeth Tully, 1896.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1806-1858. II. Personal Papers, 1808-1859.
William Tully Jr. (1785-1859)
William Tully was born at Saybrook Point, Connecticut, on November 18, 1785, the son of Colonel William Tully, and the great-grandson of John Tully, a publisher of almanacs at Saybrook in the eighteenth century. Tully entered Yale College in 1802 and graduated in 1806, after which he studied medicine with Dr. Mason Fitch Cogswell in Hartford. He was granted an A.M. degree from Yale in 1807. In 1808 and 1809 he studied with Dr. Nathan Smith at the medical school at Dartmouth College, and in 1810 with Dr. Samuel Carter in Saybrook and Dr. Eli Ives in New Haven, where he gave particular attention to botany. In October 1810 Tully was licensed to practice medicine in Connecticut. Yale awarded him an honorary M.D. in 1819, as did the Medical College of South Carolina in 1843.
Between 1810 and 1824 Tully practiced medicine in the Connecticut towns of Milford, Enfield, Cromwell, Middletown, and East Hartford, before being appointed as president and professor at the Vermont Academy of Medicine at Castleton; he remained on the faculty until 1838, though he stepped down as president in 1830.
In January 1826 Tully moved to Albany, New York, and formed a practice with Dr. Alden March, a colleague at Castleton. In September 1829 he was appointed to the faculty of medicine at Yale and moved to New Haven, although holding a dual appointment with the Vermont Academy of Medicine. In 1842 Tully resigned from the faculty at Yale, and in 1851 moved with his wife Mary Potter Tully (died 1853) to Springfield, Massachusetts. He died there on February 28, 1859, at the age of 73.
Biographical information taken from "The Peregrinating Dr. William Tully, A.M., M.D.," by H. B. Ferris, in the Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine 5, no. 1 (October 1932), and "William Tully" in Franklin Bowditch Dexter, Biographical Sketches of the Graduates of Yale College, volume 6 (New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1885-1912), pages 68-73; the latter includes a bibliography of Tully's publications.
Related Materials
William Tully's three Yale diplomas were removed in 1937 for the Yale Memorabilia Collection, and are in the Yale Diploma Collection (RU 150), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library. His Yale College Class of 1806 class album (Vault Yb71 806t), is also in Manuscripts and Archives.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence between Tully and his colleagues, primarily medical colleagues, and with the medical schools in which he taught. Also present is Tully's autograph diary covering the three months he spent studying medicine with Nathan Smith in Hanover, New Hampshire, drafts of his writings, two catalogues of his library, and a group of certificates and and diplomas he received from schools and professional societies.
Physicians -- Connecticut; Diaries -- United States -- 19th century; Diplomas -- Greece -- 19th century; Physicians -- Connecticut -- 19th century; Benedict, Noah Bennet, 1771-1831; Miner, Thomas, 1777-1841; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Tully, William, 1785-1859; Woodward, Samuel B. (Samuel Bayard), 1787-1850; Woodward, Theodore, 1788-1840; Iatrikē Hetaireia Athēnōn; College of Physicians and Surgeons of the Western District of the State of New-York; Medical College of the State of South Carolina; New Orleans Academy of Sciences; Vermont Academy of Medicine (Castleton, Vt.); Yale College (1718-1887). Medical Institution
- Correspondence, 1806-1858; Series I; 41
  - Letters to William Tully
    - Ames, Julius Rubens, 1836-06-13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Association of American Geologists, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Letter from Benjamin Silliman (1816-1885) regarding Tully's election to membership; accompanied by a copy of Tully's reply.
    - Barnard, Henry, 1838-11-29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Beers, Nathan, 1815-09-04 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Boardman, Giles M., 1834-1841 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Boardman, Henry Elisha, 1835-12-30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bronson, Henry, 1836-07-08 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Childs, Henry Halsey, 1834-12-12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cobb, Daniel G., 1856-07-23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - College of Physicians and Surgeons of the Western District of the State of New-York, 1829- (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dickson, Samuel Henry, 1835-10-28 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fish, Henry, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Hicks, T. B., 1835-04-24 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Hopkins Medical Association, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Letter from corresponding secretary Milo Linus North; accompanied by a copy of Tully's reply.
    - Howe, Hezekiah, 1829-09-18 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Jocelyn, Nathaniel, 1858-12-02 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Medical Society of the County of Albany (N.Y.), 1828- (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Miner, Thomas, 2nd, 1841- (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Thomas Miner 2nd (1800-1873) was a cousin of Dr. Thomas Miner (1777-1841); letters concern the death of Dr. Miner and the bequest of his library to William Tully.
    - New Orleans Academy of Sciences, 1856-1858 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Letters from Noah Bennet Benedict regarding Tully's election to the New Orleans Academy of Sciences; accompanied by Benedict's card, copies of Tully's letter to the registrar of the academy, and Tully's membership certificate.
    - Nott, Abraham Nott, 1833-12-19 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Phi Beta Kappa. Connecticut Alpha (Yale College), 1829 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Letter from Isaac H. Townsend, corresponding secretary; accompanied by a copy of Tully's reply.
    - Robertson, John Brownlee, 1835- (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Letters concerning a chair of chemistry at the Medical College of the State of South Carolina; accompanied by a draft of Tully's reply.
    - Sibley, Nehemiah C., 1834-04-10 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Stoutenburgh, Abraham, 1830-01-05 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Strong, John McCurdy, 1806-08-06 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Vermont Academy of Medicine, 1828-1829 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Letter of appointment to the faculty of the medical school at Castleton, Vermont, signed by Zimri Howe; accompanied by a copy of Tully's reply to the academy, and his two letters to Theodore Woodward.
      Also present is a circular letter (May 23, 1825) regarding Tully's resignation, an undated proof print of a newspaper advertisement for the academy, and an undated letter to Tully from a group of academy students.
    - Wells, Landon, 1841, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Whiting, Nathan, 1816- (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Whitridge, Joshua Barker, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Accompanied by a copy of Tully's reply.
    - Whittlesey, Chester, 1836-02-24 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Woodward, Samuel B. (Samuel Bayard), 1841- (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Woodward, Theodore, 1838-01-10 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Yale College, Medical Institution, 1829-1843 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Regarding his appointment as professor; includes letters to and from the committee of nomination, Jeremiah Day, Eli Ives, Jonathan Knight, and Benjamin Silliman. Also present are three letters to Tully regarding his teaching, two from Yale medical students and one from his colleagues Charles Hooker and Jonathan Knight.
  - Letters from William Tully
    - Cogswell, Mason Fitch, 1814, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Other correspondents, 1851-1855 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Single letters to M. C. Hazen, Ansel W. Ives, Jonathan Knight, and Constantine Samuel Rafinesque.
  - Third-party correspondence
    The subseries contains letters written between Dr. Tully's colleagues; most refer in some way to Dr. Tully.
    - Hooker, Charles, to Thomas Miner, 1824-03-24 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Regarding a position as head of the Bloomingdale Asylum for the Insane in New York; Hooker's letter to Miner was written at the end of a letter from John Stearns to Hooker.
    - Ives, Eli, to Thomas Miner, 1829-04-09 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Regarding Tully's appointment at Yale; accompanied by Tully's autograph notes explaining the letter.
    - Miner, Thomas, to Daniel McGregor, 1826-05-26 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Three-page autobiographical letter from Miner to his friend Dr. McGregor.
    - Miner, Thomas, to Nathan B. Ives, 1839-05-22 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Regarding Sawyer's Mental Philosophy.
    - Seeger, Edwin, to unidentifed, 1855-04-09 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Woodward, Theodore, to Alden March, 1828-12-29 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Personal Papers, 1808-1859; Series II; 11
  - Journal, 1808-1809 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Autograph diary of Tully's journey from Saybrook, Connecticut, to Hanover, New Hampshire, in September 1808 to study medicine, and his journey back to Saybrook in January 1809. In the pages between he wrote of his life in Hanover and his classes at Dartmouth with Dr. Nathan Smith.
    The diary was edited by Oliver S. Hayward and Elizabeth H. Thomson, and published as The Journal of William Tully, Medical Student at Dartmouth, 1808-1809, with a foreword by John F. Fulton (New York: Science History Publications, 1977).
  - Notes and drafts on scientific and medical topics, 1834-1852 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "Catalogue of the Names of Certain Plants", 1833 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Booklet in paper wrappers with autograph notes on plants.
  - "Catalogue of Library of William Tully, M.D.", undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Booklet in wrappers with manuscript listing of book titles, citations, and sizes.
  - Catalogue of an Extensive Collection of Scientific, Medical and Miscellaneous Books, being the private library of the late Dr. Wm. Tully (New York: George A. Leavitt & Co., 1859) (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "Epitaph on my Friend and Class Mate LHT", undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Manuscript transcript of an epitaph for Tully's classmate Leverett Hubbard Trumbull (Yale 1806) who died on May 7, 1807. The inscription was composed by his father and appears on his gravestone in Old North Cemetery, Hartford.
  - Sample texts for diplomas and sample diploma, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Manuscript texts copied from diplomas issued by Brown University, Middlebury College, and Transylvania University, with manuscript layout for a Vermont Academy of Medicine diploma and an engraved certificate issued by the Connecticut Medical Society to Franklin Skidmore. Also present is a blue silk ribbon with a Vermont Academy paper seal from an academy diploma.
  - Certificates and honors, 1810-1825 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Contains certificates and awards from medical societies, and Tully's military appointment as surgeon of the Sixth Regiment of the Connecticut Militia.
  - Certificates and diplomas, 1835-1854 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 50)
    Membership certificates for Lyceum of Natural History of New-York, Medical Society of the State of New-York, New Orleans Academy of Sciences, and Iatrikē Hetaireia Athēnōn (the Athens Medical Society), and a diplomas from the Medical College of South Carolina.
  - "Scutellaria-Lateriflora. Scull-Cap" by William Tully, in Middlesex Gazette, vol. 35, no 1827, 1820-11-30 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 51)
  - Newspaper clippings with "Reviewers Reviewed" and reply, regarding Miner and Tully on fever, 1824- (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 52)